Phillip: It’s inevitable that sometimes
an organisation and the people in it,
will have different values and attitudes.
When this happens, it can be difficult to
find the best solution for everyone, after
all everyone in the organisation is expected
to observe the organisation’s values.
Maddy: As a team leader, you might
find yourself in this situation and
that your loyalties are conflicted.
On one hand, it is important to keep the
organisation united and effective, but on the
other hand, people in the organisation have the
right to express their own opinions, including
disagreements with organisational values.
If you tell your team that you
won’t tolerate disagreement with the
organisational values, that won’t encourage
them to think freely and innovatively.
But conversely, if you allow people to
disregard what the organisation expects
from them, this will damage the work
you need to do and your team’s cohesion.
Phillip: When a clash emerges,
people pull in different directions.
Whatever the clash is about, the fact
that you’ve lost that unity, means that
things are going to start going wrong.
You no longer have a single clear pathway
to achieve your goals, and people will start
doing things in different ways, causing
confusion, which can have ‘knock on’ effects.
Targets may be missed and
resentments between people can grow.
Maddy: So, let’s have a
look at an example of this:
Suppose a new person starts in sales.
They have a great track record and
lots of experience and they really
want to make a good first impression.
The company really values honesty and building
long-term relationships, having a small
number of loyal clients they can rely on
rather than the uncertainty of a working with
a lot of unknown clients on small projects.
The new person, however, has different values,
they believe in getting as big a roster
of clients as possible, even if that means
stretching the truth about what can be delivered.
Although they would never tell an outright
lie, they believe that being a bit economical
with the truth and making the occasional
exaggeration, is just good sales strategy.
Phillip: What we see here is a conflict in
individual values and organisational expectations,
and this could cause resentment from other
members of the sales team if they perceive the
new person to be breaking the rules they follow.
This could also cause big problems with
production if they introduce far more clients
than the organisation is set up to expect.
In a word, this could cause problems,
which in turn could cause more problems…
This shows a clash in values.
The new person’s values, focus on bringing
in as many clients as possible, while the
organisation’s, are focused on building
strong relationships with a small number
of clients, and these are incompatible.
Maddy: As a team leader, in a situation like
this, you’d need to make sure the organisation’s
values are being clearly communicated to
everyone in the team from the beginning.
You might want to consider sending out
emails explaining what the values are and
why they matter, putting posters up about the
values, or giving presentations about them.
This will help to keep people on track and stop
conflicts from happening in the first place.
Phillip: Ignoring the problem
won’t help resolve it.
Instead, you should start by talking to the
people involved, and encouraging them to
express what their values are whilst reminding
them what the organisation expects from them.
You should also make sure you remind
them why these values exist, and
what they’re intended to achieve.
This will help them understand
that the values aren’t arbitrary.
Maddy: You should also look to see if you
can find some common ground, and if there
are principles, they may be willing to adapt.
It’s always best to try and find a
compromise if you can, but not at the
expense of the organisational values.
Phillip: You may even end up having to find a
different role for the person in the organisation,
where their values don’t cause conflict.
If we consider our example, in this case
maybe the new person in sales, would be
better suited to working in marketing.
Maddy: And if all else fails and the problem
doesn’t go away, you may have no other option
than to formally escalate it as a disciplinary
matter, but always make sure you follow
your organisation’s policies for doing this.